My name is Harry Baker. Harry Baker is my name.
اسمي هاري بيكر. هاري بيكر هو اسمي.
If your name was Harry Baker, then our names would be the same.
إن كان اسمك هاري بيكر، فأسماؤنا ستكون متشابهة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's a short introductory part.
إنه مقطع افتتاحي قصير.
Yeah, I'm Harry.
نعم. أنا هاري.
I study maths. I write poetry.
أدرس الرياضيات وأكتب الشعر.
So I thought I'd start with a love poem about prime numbers.
لذا اعتقدت أنني سأبدأ بقصيدة حب حول الأعداد الأولية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is called "59."
هذا يُدعى "59".
I was going to call it "Prime Time Loving."
كنت سأسميه "عاشق الأرقام الأولية."
That reaction is why I didn't.
ردة الفعل هذه هي السبب في عدم فعل ذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, "59."
إذًا، "59".
59 wakes up on the wrong side of the bed.
يصحو 59 على الجانب الخاطئ من السرير.
Realizes all his hair is on one side of his head.
يدرك أن كل شعره على جانب واحد من رأسه.
Takes just under a minute to work out that it’s because of the way that he slept.
يستغرق أقل من دقيقة ليفهم أن هذا بسبب الطريقة التي نام بها.
He finds some clothes and gets dressed.
يجد بعض الملابس ويقوم بارتدائها.
He can’t help but look in the mirror and be subtly impressed
لا يستطيع أن يقاوم النظر للمرآة وإبداء إعجابه الكبير
How he looks rough around the edges and yet casually messed.
بمظهره الذي يبدو فيه حادًا عند الحواف، وأشعث من غير تكلف.
And as he glances out the window, he sees the sight that he gets blessed with
وعندما ينظر من خلال النافذة، يرى منظرًا يشعر فيه أنه في نعمة،
of 60 from across the street.
منظر 60 في الشارع.
Now 60 was beautiful.
كانت 60 جميلة.
With perfectly trimmed cuticles, dressed in something suitable.
ببشرة مزينة بشكل مثالي، ترتدي أشياء لائقة.
Never rude or crude at all.
لم تكن وقحة أو فظة إطلاقًا.
Unimprovable, right on time as usual, more on cue than a snooker ball
فهي مثالية، دقيقة في مواعيدها كالعادة، تحب البلياردو أكثر من السنوكر
but liked to play it super cool.
ولكنها أحبت أن تلعبها من غير مبالاة.
59 wanted to tell her that he knew her favorite flower.
أراد 59 أن يخبرها أنه عرف وردتها المفضلة.
He thought of her every second, every minute, every hour.
فكّر فيها كل ثانية، كل دقيقة، كل ساعة.
But he knew it wouldn’t work, he’d never get the girl.
لكنه علم أن ذلك لن يجدي نفعًا، لن يحصل على الفتاة أبدًا.
Because although she lived across the street
لأنها على الرغم من سكنها في الشارع المقابل
they came from different worlds.
إلا أنهم أتوا من عوالم مختلفة.
While 59 admired 60’s perfectly round figure,
بينما أُعجب 59 بشكل الـ 60 المدور بإتقان،
60 thought 59 was odd. (Laughter)
اعتقدت 60 أن 59 كان غريب الأطوار. (ضحك)
One of his favorite films was "101 Dalmatians."
كان "101 مرقش" أحد أفلامه المفضلة.
She preferred the sequel.
هي فضلت النتيجة.
He romanticized the idea they were star-crossed lovers.
هو جعل من فكرة كونهما عاشقين غير محظوظين أمرًا رومانسيًا.
They could overcome the odds and evens because they had each other.
بإمكانهما التغلب على الفروقات لأنهما يملكان بعضهما الآخر.
While she maintained the strict views imposed on her by her mother
وبينما هي التزمت الآراء المتشددة التي تفرضها أمها عليها،
That separate could not be equal.
فإن ذلك الفرق لم يمكن يكون متساويا.
And though at the time he felt stupid and dumb
وبالرغم من الوقت الذي شعر فيه بالغباء
For trying to love a girl controlled by her stupid mum,
لمحاولته أن يحب فتاة منقادة لأمها الغبية،
He should have been comforted by the simple sum.
كان يتوجب عليه مواساة نفسه بالمعادلة البسيطة.
Take 59 away from 60, and you’re left with the one.
خذ 59 بعيدًا عن 60، وستبقى مع واحدة.
Sure enough after two months of moping around,
بالتأكيد بعد شهرين من التسكع في الأرجاء،
61 days later, 61 was who he found,
بعد 61 يومًا، كانت 61 هي الشخص الذي وجده.
He had lost his keys and his parents were out.
لقد فقد مفاتيحه كان أبواه في الخارج.
So one day after school he went into a house
لذا في أحد الأيام بعد المدرسة دخل منزلًا
As he noticed the slightly wonky numbers on the door,
عندما لاحظ أعدادًا غريبة بعض الشيء تقف على الباب،
He wondered why he’d never introduced himself before,
تساءل لماذا لم يقدّم نفسه من قبل،
As she let him in, his jaw dropped in awe.
وعندما أدخلته، تحولت دهشته إلى خشية.
61 was like 60, but a little bit more. (Laughter)
كانت 61 مثل 60، ولكن أكثر بقليل. (ضحك)
She had prettier eyes, and an approachable smile,
كانت تملك عيونًا أجمل، وابتسامة قريبة للقلوب.
And like him, rough around the edges, casual style,
ومثله، كانت حادةً عند الحواف، بغير تكلف.
And like him, everything was in disorganized piles,
ومثله، كان كل شيء في أكوام غير مرتبة،
And like him, her mum didn’t mind if friends stayed a while.
ومثله، لم تكن أمها تعترض إن جلس أصدقائها قليلًا.
Because she was like him, and he liked her.
لأنها كانت مثله، ولأنه أحبها،
He reckoned she would like him if she knew he was like her,
ظنّ بأنها ستحبه لو علمت أنه يحبها.
And it was different this time. I mean, this girl was wicked,
وكان الأمر مختلفًا هذه المرة. أقصد، كانت هذه الفتاة خبيثة،
So he plucked up the courage and asked for her digits.
لذا استجمع قواه وطلب منها أرقامها.
She said, "I'm 61." He grinned, said, "I'm 59."
قالت "أنا 61". ابتسم قائلًا "أنا 59".
Today I’ve had a really nice time,
لقد استمتعت اليوم بحق،
So tomorrow if you wanted you could come over to mine?
لذا إن رغبتِ يمكنك القدوم لمنزلي؟
She said, "Sure."
قالت "نعم".
She loved talking to someone just as quirky,
هي أحبت الحديث إلى شخص غير تقليدي.
She agreed to this unofficial first date.
وافقت على الموعد الأول غير الرسمي.
In the end he was only ready one minute early,
في النهاية، كان مستعدا قبل دقيقة من الموعد،
But it didn’t matter because she arrived one minute late.
ولكن ذلك لم يهم لأنها وصلت بعد دقيقة.
And from that moment on there was nonstop chatter,
كان الحديث مستمرًا منذ تلك اللحظة،
How they loved "X Factor," how they had two factors,
كيف أحبا "إكس فاكتور"، كيف كان لديهما عاملين،
How that did not matter, distinctiveness made them better,
كيف أن ذلك لا يهم، التمييز جعلها أفضل.
By the end of the night they knew they were meant together.
وفي نهاية الليلة، علما أنه مقدر أن يكونا معًا.
And one day she was talking about stuck-up 60,
وبأحد الأيام، كانت تتحدث عن المغرورة 60،
She noticed that 59 looked a bit shifty.
ولاحظت أن 59 بدا مراوغا بعض الشيء.
He blushed, told her of his crush:
هو استحى وأخبرها عن افتتانه بها:
“The best thing that never happened because it led to us.”
"إنه أفضل شيء لم يحصل لأنه جعلنا معًا".
61 was clever, see, not prone to jealousy,
كانت 61 ذكية، تفهمون، لا تستسلم للغيرة.
She looked him in the eyes and told him quite tenderly,
نظرت في عيونه وأخبرته برقة شديدة
"You’re 59, I’m 61, together we combine to become twice what 60 could ever be."
"أنت 59 وأنا 61 ومعًا نجتمع لنصبح ضعف ما يستطيع 60 أن يكون عليه".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
At this point 59 had tears in his eyes,
عند هذه النقطة، كانت الدموع تملأ عيون 59،
Was so glad to have this one-of-a-kind girl in his life.
كان سعيدًا لامتلاكه هذه الفتاة الفريدة في حياته.
He told her the very definition of being prime
أخبرها أن التعريف الدقيق لكونه أوليًا
Was that with only one and himself could his heart divide,
هو أنه لا يمكن لقلبه أن يقسم إلاّ على واحد وعلى نفسه،
And she was the one he wanted to give his heart to,
وأنها الرقم واحد الذي يريد أن يعطيها قلبه.
She said she felt the same and now she knew the films were half true.
أخبرته أنها شعرت بنفس الإحساس وعرفت الآن أن الأفلام كان نصف حقيقية.
Because that wasn't real love, that love was just a sample,
لأن ذلك لم يكن حبا حقيقيا، كان ذلك الحب مجرد نموذج،
When it came to real love, they were a prime example.
عندما نتطرق إلى الحب الحقيقي، كان ذلك الحب مثل الأعداد الأولية.
Cheers.
في صحتكم!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
That was the first poem that I wrote
كانت هاته أول قصيدة أكتبها
and it was for a prime number-themed poetry night -- (Laughter) --
وكانت من أجل ليلة الشعر حول الأعداد الأولية -- (ضحك) --
which turned out to be a prime number-themed poetry competition.
والتي تبين أنها مسابقة شعرية حول الأعداد الأولية.
And I became a prime number-themed poetry competition winner,
وأصبحت الفائز في هذه المسابقة الشعرية،
or as I like to call it, a prime minister. (Laughter)
أو كما أحب أن أسمي نفسي رئيس الوزراء. (ضحك)
And this is how I discovered these things called poetry slams,
وبهذه الطريقة اكتشفت هذه الأشياء التي تعرف بشعر الصلام،
and if you don't know what a poetry slam is,
وإن كنتم لا تعرفون ما معنى شعر الصلام،
it was a format come up with in America 30 years ago
هو نوع ظهر في أمريكا منذ 30 عاما
as a way of tricking people into going to poetry events
كوسيلة لخداع الناس ودفعهم لحضور المسابقات الشعرية
by putting an exciting word like "slam" on the end.
بوضع كلمات مثيرة مثل "الصفعة" في آخر الكلام.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And each performer got three minutes to perform
ويملك كل مؤدي ثلاث دقائق لتقديم أدائه،
and then random audience members would hold up scorecards,
و بعد ذلك يحمل افراد عشوائيون من الجمهور بطاقات التقييم،
and they would end up with a numerical score,
و ينتهي الأمر بالنتيجة الرقمية ،
and what this meant is,
و ما يهدف اليه ذلك ،
it kind of broke down the barrier between performer and audience
هو نوعا ما كسر للحاجز الموجود بين المؤدي و الجمهور
and encouraged the kind of connection with the listener.
ويشجع هذا الترابط الموجود مع المستمعين .
And what it also means is you can win.
و يعني ذلك ايضاً انه يمكنك الفوز .
And if you win a poetry slam, you can call yourself a slam champion
و إذا فزت في مسابقة الشعر ، يمكنك ان تسمي نفسك "ملك الصفع"
and pretend you're a wrestler,
و تظاهر بأنك مصارع ،
and if you lose a poetry slam you can say, "Oh, what? Poetry's a subjective art form,
وإذا خسرت في مباراة الإلقاء يمكنك ان تقول "ما هذا؟ الشعر من أشكال الفن الغير موضوعي
you can't put numbers on such things."
لا يمكنك ان تضع رقم علي شيء كهذا."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I loved it, and I got involved in these slams,
ولكني احبه ، فقد انخرطت في هذه الجولات ،
and I became the U.K. slam champion
الى أن أصبحت بطل مباريات الشعر في المملكة المتحدة
and got invited to the Poetry World Cup in Paris,
و تم دعوتي الى كأس العالم للشعر في باريس.
which was unbelievable.
و هو شيء لا يصدق .
It was people from all around the world speaking in their native languages
كان يوجد أشخاص من جميع أنحاء العالم يتحدثون بلغاتهم الأصلية
to be judged by five French strangers.
وستكون لجنة التحكيم متكونة من 5 غرباء فرنسيين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And somehow, I won, which was great,
وبطريقة ما، فزت وقد كان هذا أمرا رائعا،
and I've been able to travel the world since doing it,
ومنذ ذلك الحين تمكنت من السفر حول العالم،
but it also means that this next piece
ولكن ذلك يعني أن هذه القطعة التالية
is technically the best poem in the world.
تعتبر من الناحية الفنية أفضل قصيدة في العالم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So...
بالتالي...
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
According to five French strangers.
وفقا لخمسة غرباء فرنسيين.
So this is "Paper People."
هذه "الشخصيات الورقية".
I like people.
أحب الناس.
I'd like some paper people.
أحببت بعض الشخصيات الورقية.
They’d be purple paper people. Maybe pop-up purple paper people.
كانت هناك شخصيات ورقية أرجوانية اللون. ربما لونها أرجواني بارز.
Proper pop-up purple paper people.
شخصيات ورقية لونها أرجواني بارز مناسب.
"How do you prop up pop-up purple paper people?"
"كيف تقوم بدعم شخصيات ورقية لونها أرجواني بارز؟"
I hear you cry. Well I ...
أسمع بكائكم. حسنا، أنا...
I’d probably prop up proper pop-up purple paper people
قدمت الدعم المناسب لشخصياتٍ ورقية لونها أرجواني بارز
with a proper pop-up purple people paperclip,
بإعتماد مشبك للشخصيات ذات لون أرجواني بارز،
but I’d pre-prepare appropriate adhesives as alternatives,
ولكن قمت بالإعداد المسبق المناسب فأحضرت موادا لاصقة كبديلٍ
a cheeky pack of Blu Tack just in case the paper slipped.
عبلة من بلو تاك ممتلئة فقط في حالة انفصال الأوراق عن بعضها.
Because I could build a pop-up metropolis.
لأنه يمكنني بناء مدينة فجأة.
but I wouldn’t wanna deal with all the paper people politics.
ولكن لا أريد التعامل مع كل سياسات الشخصيات الورقية.
paper politicians with their paper-thin policies,
الشخصيات السياسية الورقية وسياستهم الورقية الهزيلة
broken promises without appropriate apologies.
وعودهم الكاذبة بدون تقديم الإعتذارات المناسبة.
There’d be a little paper me. And a little paper you.
كانت ستوجد ورقة صغيرة لي. وأخرى صغيرة لك.
And we could watch paper TV and it would all be pay-per-view.
ويمكننا مشاهدة التلفزيون الورقي وسيكون تعريفة لكل مشهد.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We’d see the poppy paper rappers rap about their paper package
كنا سنشاهد مغني الراب الورقيين من الخشخاش يغننون الراب حول حزمة الورق
or watch paper people carriers get stuck in paper traffic on the A4.
أو مشاهدة الناقلات الورقية للأشخاص تعلق في حركة المرور للأوراق بحجم A4.
(Laughter) Paper.
(ضحك) ورقة.
There’d be a paper princess Kate but we’d all stare at paper Pippa,
يوجد أميرة ورقية تدعى كيت ولكننا نقوم جميع بالتحديق في الورقة بيبا،
and then we’d all live in fear of killer Jack the Paper-Ripper,
وبعدها عشنا في خوف من القاتل جاك المعروف بممزق الورق،
because the paper propaganda propagates the people's prejudices,
لأن الورق الدعاية ينشر الأفكار المسبقة للناس.
papers printing pictures of the photogenic terrorists.
تقوم الأوراق بطباعة صور للإرهابيين الجذابين فوتوغرافيا.
A little paper me. And a little paper you.
ورقة صغيرة لي. وأخرى صغيرة لك.
And in a pop-up population people’s problems pop up too.
وتظهر أيضا مشاكل الناس فجأة في المجتمعات المنبثقة.
There’d be a pompous paper parliament who remained out of touch,
سيكون هناك برلمان ورقي فخم الذي لا يمكن الوصول إليه،
and who ignored the people's protests about all the paper cuts,
والذي يتجاهل احتجاجات الشعب حول التخفيض في ثمن الورق،
then the peaceful paper protests would get blown to paper pieces,
ثم سيتعرض الشعوب المحتجة سلميا لهجوم ليصبحوا قطعا ورقية،
by the confetti cannons manned by pre-emptive police.
هجوم بواسطة مدافع قصاصات ورقية تديرها الشرطة الوقائية.
And yes there’d still be paper money, so there’d still be paper greed,
ونعم لا زال هناك نقود ورقية بالتالي لازال هناك طمع ورقي،
and the paper piggy bankers pocketing more than they need,
ويضع المصرفييون الشجعون في جيوبهم أكثر مما يحتاجون،
purchasing the potpourri to pepper their paper properties,
شراء خليط من الأوراق لنثرها على الممتلكات الورقية،
others live in poverty and ain’t acknowledged properly.
آخرون يعيشون في خصاصة ولا يعترف بهم بشكل سليم.
A proper poor economy where so many are proper poor,
ضعف اقتصادي مناسب حيث أن الكثير منهم فقراء بشكل خاص،
but while their needs are ignored the money goes to big wars.
ولكن بينما يتم تجاهل احتياجاتهم يذهب المال للحروب الكبيرة.
Origami armies unfold plans for paper planes
تكشف جيوش الأوريغامي خطط الطائرات الورقية
and we remain imprisoned in our own paper chains,
ونظل رهن الاحتجاز داخل قيودنا الورقية،
but the greater shame is that it always seems to stay the same,
ولكن العار الأكبر أن الأمر يبدو دائما على حاله،
what changes is who’s in power choosing how to lay the blame,
ما تغير هو من كان على رأس السلطة وطريقة إلقاء اللوم،
they’re naming names, forgetting these are names of people,
يقومون بتسمية الأشياء، متناسين أنها أسماء أشخاص،
because in the end it all comes down to people.
لأنه في نهاية المطاف ينهار كل شيء على الناس.
I like people.
أحب الناس.
'Cause even when the situation’s dire,
لأنه حتى عندما يصبح الوضح فادحا،
it is only ever people who are able to inspire,
يتمكن الناس فقط من أن يصبحوا قادرين على الإلهام،
and on paper, it’s hard to see how we all cope.
وعلى الورق، من الصعب أن نرى كيف نتعاون جميعا.
But in the bottom of Pandora’s box there’s still hope,
ولكن في الجزء السفلي من صندوق باندورا لا يزال هناك أمل،
and I still hope 'cause I believe in people.
وما زلت آمل لأنني أثق في الناس.
People like my grandparents.
أشخاص مثل أجدادي.
Who every single day since I was born,
الذي يوميا منذ ولدت،
have taken time out of their morning to pray for me.
يخصصون وقتا في الصباح من أجل الصلاة والدعاء لي.
That’s 7892 days straight of someone checking I’m okay,
هذا هو اليوم 7892 على التوالي الذي يوم شخص بالتأكد من أنني بخير،
and that’s amazing.
وهذا أمر مدهش.
People like my aunt who puts on plays with prisoners.
أشخاص مثل عمتي يتظاهرون باللعب مع السجناء.
People who are capable of genuine forgiveness.
الناس القادرون على الصفح بشكل حقيقي.
People like the persecuted Palestinians.
أشخاص مثل الفلسطينيين المضطهدين.
People who go out of their way to make your life better,
الناس الذين يخرجون عن طريقهم لجعل حياتك أفضل،
and expect nothing in return.
ويتوقعون شيئا في المقابل.
You see, people have potential to be powerful.
أترى، أشخاص يملكون القدرة أن يكونوا أقوياء.
Just because the people in power tend to pretend to be victims
فقط لأن من في السلطة تميل إلى التظاهر بأنهم ضحايا
we don’t need to succumb to that system.
نحن لسنا بحاجة إلى الخضوع لهذا النظام.
And a paper population is no different.
والمجتمعات الورقية ليست مختلفة.
There’s a little paper me. And a little paper you.
هذه ورقة صغيرة لي. وأخرى صغيرة لك.
And in a pop-up population people's problems pop up too,
وتظهر أيضا مشاكل الناس فجأة في المجتمعات المنبثقة.
but even if the whole world fell apart then we’d still make it through.
وحتى وإن سقط العالم بأكمله لازلنا نقوم بذلك حتى النهاية.
Because we’re people.
لأننا شعب.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you very much. I've just got time for one more.
شكرا جزيلا. حصلت على وقت إضافي من أجل واحدة أخرى.
For me, poetry has been the ultimate way of ideas without frontiers.
بالنسبة لي، يعتبر الشعر الوسيلة الأساسية لأفكار بلا حدود.
When I first started,
عندما بدأت بذلك،
the people who inspired me were the ones with the amazing stories,
الناس التي ألهمتني كانوا أولئك الذين يملكون قصصا مذهلة،
and I thought, as an 18-year-old with a happy life, it was too normal,
وكصبي في 18 من عمره يعيش حياة سعيدة، إعتقدت أن هذا أمرا طبيعيٌّ،
but I could create these worlds where I could talk about my experiences
ولكن يمكنني بناء هذه العوامل أين يمكنني أن أتحدث عن تجاربي
and dreams and beliefs.
وعن أحلامي ومعتقداتي.
So it's amazing to be here in front of you today.
حيث أنه من المدهش أن أكون هنا أمامكم اليوم.
Thank you for being here.
شكرا لوجودكم هنا.
If you weren't here,
لولا وجودكم،
it would be pretty much like the sound check yesterday.
لكان الأمر يشبه اختبار الصوت الذي قمنا به البارحة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And this is more fun.
وهذا ممتع أكثر.
So this last one is called "The Sunshine Kid."
تسمى هذه القصيدة الأخيرة "الطفل المشرق".
Thank you very much for listening.
شكرا جزيلا على إنصاتكم.
Old man sunshine was proud of his sun,
كان رجل عجوز سعيد فخور بشمسه،
And it brightened his day to see his little boy run,
وتشرق أيامه عندما يرى ابنه الصغير يركض،
Not because of what he’d done, nor the problems overcome,
ليس بما قد فعله، ولا المشاكل التي تغلب عليها،
But that despite that his disposition remained a sunny one.
ولكن هذا على الرغم من أن تصرفاته ظلت متفائلة.
It hadn’t always been like this.
لم يكن الوضع على هذا النحو دائما.
There’d been times when he’d tried to hide his brightness,
كانت هناك أوقات يحاول فيها إخفاء إشراقه،
You see, every star hits periods of hardship,
كما ترون، تمر كل النجوم بفترات صعبة.
It takes a brighter light to inspire them through the darkness.
يحتاج ضوءا أكثر إشراقا لإلهامهم في الظلام.
If we go back to when he was born in a nebula,
وإذا عدنا للفترة التي ولد فيها في السديم،
We know that he never was thought of as regular,
ونعلم أنه لم يعتقد أبدا أنه شيء عادي،
Because he had a flair about him,
لأنه يملك ميلا تجاهه،
To say the Midas touch is wrong
أن نقول أن الملك ميداس لمسه خطأ
But all he went near seemed to turn a little bronze,
ولكن كل من يحذو بالقرب منه يتحول قليلا إلى البرونز.
Yes this sun was loved by some more than others,
ونعم فقد كانت هذه الشمس محبوبة من البعض أكثر من غيرهم.
It was a case of Joseph and his dreamcoat and his brothers
كانت تشبه قصة يوسف وحلمه وإخوانه
Because standing out from the crowd had its pros and its cons,
لأن الخروج عن الحشد له إيجابياته وسلبياته.
And jealousy created enemies in those he outshone
وتتسبب الغيرة في ظهور أعداء لأولئك الذين يتألقون
Such as the Shadow People.
كالأشخاص المتخفين في الظل.
Now the Shadow People didn’t like the Sunshine Kid,
يكره الآن الأشخاص المتخفون الطفل المشرق،
Because he showed up the dark things the Shadow People did,
لأنه يكشف الأشياء المظلمة التي قام بها الأشخاص المتخفين.
And when he shone he showed the places where the Shadow People hid,
وعندما يشرق يكشف عن الأماكن التي يختفون فيها.
So the Shadow People had an evil plan to get rid of him,
لذلك قاموا بوضع خطة للتخلص منه،
First up -- they made fun of his sunspots,
أولا-- سخروا من الكلفة الشمسية التي لديه،
Shooting his dreams from the sky, their words were gunshots,
يترصدون بأحلامه من السماء، كانت كلماتهم كالطلقات النارية،
Designed to remind him he wasn’t very cool
صممت لتذكيره أنه لم يكن مميزا جدا
And he didn’t fit in with any popular kids at school.
وأنه لا يصل لمستوى لشهرة أي طفل في المدرسة.
They said his head was up in space and they would bring him down to Earth,
كانوا يقولون أنه مغرور جدا وأنهم سيجبرونه على التخلص منه،
Essentially he came from nothing and that is what he was worth,
خاصة وأنه أتى من لا شيء وهذا ما يستحقه،
He’d never get to go to university to learn,
لم يتمكن أبدا من الذهاب إلى الجامعة للتعلم،
Only degrees he’d ever show would be the first degree burns
الدرجات التي قام بإبرازها هي حروق من الدرجة الأولى
From those that came too close,
من أولئك الذين اقتربوا منه كثيرا،
they told him he was too bright,
أخبروه أنه كان مشرقا للغاية،
That’s why no one ever looked him in the eyes,
لهذا السبب لم يتجرأ أحد للنظر إليه في عينيه،
His judgment became clouded
أصبح حكمه محجوبا
So did the sky, With evaporated tears
وكذلك أصبحت السماء، بفعل الدموع المتبخرة
as the sun started to cry.
كأن الشمس بدأت في البكاء.
Because the sunshine kid was bright, with a warm personality,
لأن الطفل المشرق ساطعا وذكيا، بشخصية دافئة،
And inside he burned savagely
ويحترق بوحشية من الداخل
Hurt by the words and curses of the shadowy folk
حيث أنه تأذى بكلمات وشتائم القوم الغامضين
who spoke holes in his soul and left cavities,
الذين تحدثوا بالسوء عنه وغادروا مخلفين فجوات،
And as his heart hardened, his spark darkened,
وكلما تحجر قلبه خفت بريقه،
Every time they called him names it cooled his flames,
كل مرة أطلقوا عليه اسما تنطفأ شعلته،
He thought they might like him if he kept his light dim
كان يعتقد أنهم سيحبونه إذا ما أبقى ضوءه خافتا
But they were busy telling lightning she had terrible aim,
ولكنهم كانوا مشغولين بحديث صاعق كان الهدف رهيبا،
He couldn’t quite get to grips with what they said,
لم يتمكن من الحصول على السيطرة بما قالوه،
So he let his light be eclipsed by what they said,
لذلك سمح لنوره بالانطفاء
He fell into a Lone Star State like Texas,
سقط في ولاية النجمة الوحيدة مثل تكساس،
And felt like he’d been punched in his solar plexus.
وأحس وكأنه تم دفعه نحو انطوائه.
But that’s when Little Miss Sunshine came along
ولكن هذا عندما ظهرت الأنسة الصغيرة المشرقة تمشي وحدها
Singing her favorite song about how we’re made to be strong,
وتدندن أغنيتها المفضلة حول كيف أننا خلقنا لنكون أقوياء،
And you don’t have to be wrong to belong, Just be true to who you are,
ولم يتوجب أن تكون مخطئا في الانتماء، فقط كون صادقا لما أنت عليه،
because we are all stars at heart.
لأننا جميعا نجوم في القلب.
Little Miss Sunshine was hot stuff,
كانت الانسة الصغيرة المشرقة من الأشياء المحفزة للنفس،
The kind of girl when you looked at her
من الفتيات اللاتي إذا نظرت إليهن
you forgot stuff,
تنسى بعض الأشياء،
But for him, there was no forgetting her,
لكن بالنسبة له، لم يكن هناك سبيل لنسيانها،
The minute he saw her her image burned in his retina,
في الدقيقة التي نظر إليها أحس بأن عيناه تشتعلان،
She was out of this world, and she accepted him,
كانت من خارج عالمه، وقبلت به،
Something about this girl meant he knew whenever she was next to him,
شيء ما حول هذه الفتاة يعني أنه يعرف كلما كانت بجواره،
Things weren’t as dark as they seemed, and he dared to dream,
لم تكن الأشياء مظلمة كما كانت تبدو عليه، وتجرأ أن يحلم،
Shadows were nowhere to be seen; when she was there he beamed,
لم يكن للظلال مكان يمكن رؤيتهم فيه، عندما تكون معه يشع بهجة،
His eyes would light up in ways that can’t be faked,
تضيء عينيه بطريقة لا يمكن أن يكون ذلك كذبٌ،
When she grinned her rays erased the razor-tipped words of hate,
كلما ابتسمت محت أشعتها اثار كلمات الكراهية،
They gave each other nicknames, they were "cool star" and "fun sun,"
أطلقوا ألقابا عل أنفسهم، وقد كانت "النجمة المميزة" و"الشمس المرحة"،
And gradually the shadowy damage became undone,
وتدريجيا بدأت الآثار التي خلفتها الأظلال بالاختفاء،
She was one in a septillion, and she was brilliant,
كانت رقم 1 من بين السبتيليون، كانت رائعة،
Could turn the coldest blooded reptilians vermillion,
كان يمكنها أن تحول دم الزواحف القرمزي البارد،
Loved by billions, from Chileans to Brazilians,
محبوب من المليارات، من التشيليين إلى البرازيليين،
And taught the Sunshine Kid the meaning of resilience.
وتعلم الطفل المشرق معنى الصمود.
She said: “All the darkness in the world
وقالت: "كل الظلام في العالم
cannot put out the light from a single candle
لا يمكنه إخماد الضوء المتأتي من شمعة واحدة
So how the hell can they handle your light?
فكيف يمكنهم التعامل مع ضوئك؟
Only you can choose to dim it, and the sky is the limit,
أنت فقط يمكنك أن تختار اطفائه، والسماء هي الحد،
so silence the critics by burning.”
لذلك قم بإسكات المنتقدين بحرقهم. "
And if eyes are windows to the soul then she drew back the curtains
وإذا العيون نوافذ على الروح فإنها ستقوم بإسدال الستائر
And let the sun shine through the hurting.
والسماح للشمس بالتألق من خلال الاساءة.
In a universe of adversity these stars stuck together,
تتماسك النجوم معا في عالم المحن،
And though days became nights the memories would last forever,
وبالرغم من أن النهار يصبح ليلا إلا أن الذكريات تدوم إلى الأبد،
Whether the weatherman said it or not, it would be fine,
سواء قال خبير الأرصاد الجوية ذلك أم لا فسيكون كل شيء بخير
'Cause even behind the clouds the kid could still shine.
لأنه حتى وراء الغيوم يمكن للصبي أن يسطع.
Yes, the Sunshine Kid was bright, with a warm personality,
نعم كان الطفل المشرق ساطعا، بشخصية دافئة،
And inside he burned savagely,
ويحترق بوحشية من الداخل،
Fueled by the fire inspired across galaxies
تغذيها النار المستوحاة عبر المجرات
By the girl who showed him belief.
من الفتاة التي أظهرت له إيمانا.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)